Hi, everybody.
大家好
How we doing?
怎么样
We got caffeinated?
我们补充了咖啡因吗？
Feeling good?
感觉好吗？
Nice.
真好
So I'm Anjana Vakil, hello.
我是Anjana Vakil
You can find me on Twitter at my name and today I'd like to talk to you about immutable
你可以在Twitter上以我的名字找到我，
今天我想和你谈谈
data structures for functional programming in JavaScript.
JavaScript中，函数式编程里不可变的数据结构
We're going to take a look at what immutable data structures are, why they're a really
我们将看看什么是不变的数据结构
cool way to handle the immutability that we typically use when we're doing functional
为什么它们是函数式编程中处理不变性的好方法
programming and how we can do that in JavaScript because I hear y'all like JavaScript!
以及我们如何在JavaScript中做到这一点
因为我听说你们都喜欢JavaScript！
So a little about me.
关于我的点滴
I'm probably the only not-web-developer in the room.
我可能是这里唯一的非网络开发人员
I am an engineer for Uber Research.
我是Uber Research的工程师
I work with them to develop a custom query language for data in the scientific research
我参与开发一种自定义数据查询语言
funding domain.
用于科学研究基金领域
I'm also an alum of the Recurse Center, which is a fantastic programming community in New
我也是Recurse中心的成员。这是纽约的一个很棒的编程社区
York City, and I am an alum of the Outreach Program, which if you have haven't heard of
我也是Outreach项目的一员，你可能没听说过
it, it's getting women and more folks involved in these by giving them internships at Mozilla.
它吸引了更多的女性和少数群体参与，在Mozilla给他们提供实习机会。
So I'm really happy to chat about those things if you want to come grab me after the talk.
所以我很高兴谈论这些事情，你们可以演讲之后来找我
But you might know that I like functional programming.
但是你可能已经知道我喜欢函数式编程
I think it rocks.
我认为函数式编程很酷
Anybody else agree with me that functional programming is cool?
其他人都同意我的观点，觉得函数式编程很酷吗？
Yeah!
是的
Yeah, so functional programming is a pretty great way to avoid some of the headaches of
是的，所以函数式编程避免了很多
like imperative and object-oriented programming.
命令式和面向对象的编程的问题
In functional programming, what we typically do is conceive of our programs as being just
在函数式编程中，通常所做的只是将我们的程序视为
pure functions.
纯函数
That means their transform their inputs to outputs, and that's all they do.
这意味着他们将输入转换为输出，这就是他们所做的全部
They don't have my side effects like changing things in the console, and my taking things
他们没有副作用，在console中打印内容。或者是
in the global state are side effects.
改变全局作用域中的值
But our data becomes data in, data out, and transformers of data.
但是我们的数据变成了数据输入，数据输出和数据转换。
And one thing that goes hand-in-hand with this, with avoiding side effects is immutable
与之紧密相连的一件事，能够避免副作用的是不可变
data.
数据
Immutable data meaning once we've created it, it never changes.
不变的数据意味着我们创建之后
它，它永远不会改变。
So this is a really good way of changing something accidental outside of your function.
这能避免数据在函数外意外被改变
If everything is immutable, you can't change anything.
如果一切都是不变的，那么你就无法改变
任何东西
So immutability another thing that rocks and it rocks pretty hard for other reasons that
所以不可变性很酷，它很酷的原因是
we'll see in a moment.
我们一会儿会看到
But speaking of rocks, let's talk about rocks.
但是说到很酷，让我们谈谈岩石。
So this is a rock, and immutability rocks in the way that rocks rock.
所以这是一块岩石，而不变性和岩石一样酷
Now I don't know about you, but I've been going to a lot of tech conferences recently
我不知道你们，但是我最近参加很多技术会议
and I've been feeling like there has enough poetry.
我感到技术会议缺乏诗意
So I'd like to read you a poem: Nobody sits like this rock sits.
所以我想读一首诗：没有人像岩石一样坐着
You rock, rock.
你很酷，石头
The rock just sits and is.
岩石就此静坐
You show us how to just sit here.
你向我们展示了如何坐在这里
And that's what we need.
这就是我们所需要的
It's so true, so deep.
如此真实，如此深刻
This is from -- Don't thank me, thank I Heart Huckabees, that's
这是...不用谢谢我，谢谢《我 ❤ Huckabees》，那是
a great movie.
一部很棒的电影
Check it out.
去看看
So this is really how immutable data rocks.
因此，这确实是不可变数据的酷的地方
It just sits there.
它只是坐在那里
It just is.
就是这样
Once we've created it, it never changes and that's amazing because it can help us avoid
创建之后，它就永远不会改变。太神奇了，因为它可以帮助我们避免
some of the headaches of immutability.
可变性的一些烦恼
So with immutability, we have some things pretty easy, but other things become harder
因此，如果数据可变，我们有一些东西
很容易，但是其他事情变得更困难
and we'll see how that looks.
我们将看看它的表现
So let's say I have an array called foo and it's got some numbers in it.
假设我有一个名为foo的数组，它里面有一些数字
Hm, and I'm already bored.
嗯，我已经很无聊了
Let's make it more fun.
让我们变得更有趣
Let's say I have a zoo with some animals -- more fun!
假设我有一个动物园里有一些动物-更有趣！
And I decided that I want to change something up about my zoo.
我决定要改变动物园一些东西
Maybe I want to replace that rabbit there with something a little more exotic.
也许我想在那里替换那只兔子，换上有异国情调的东西
Like an alien!
比如外星人！
So this is cool.
所以这很酷
I'm happy because I wanted a more exotic zoo.
我很高兴，因为我想要一个更具异国情调的动物园
I got an alien in my zoo now.
我的动物园里有一个外星人
I didn't have to change anything except for that one little cell in my array.
我不需要改变任何东西，除了数组中的那个元素
That's pretty sweet but my co-worker over was expecting zoo to be filled with earth
真是太好了，但我的同事希望动物园充满地球生物
beings, earth animals, and wasn't accounting for there being an alien in it.
地球上的动物，不打算放外星人
Who put that in there?
谁把它放在那里的？
Now my program doesn't work anymore.
现在我的程序不再运行了
Who did that?
谁做的？
So immutability has a couple problems.
因此，可变性有两个问题
We have to manage who's been changing what, when -- who's been putting which animals in
我们必须管理谁在改变什么，什么时候-谁在放哪些动物
the zoo.
到动物园中
We have to have a lot of overhead to manage that state, and that gives us headaches as
我们必须管理很多开销，这让我们头疼
individuals, and as teams.
无论个人还是团队
We also get bugs in the code because maybe I was only planning -- or my co-worker was
我们还会在代码中出现错误，因为也许
我只是在计划-或者我的同事是
only planning -- to handle terrestrial beings and didn't have a case of aliens being accounted
仅计划-处理陆地生物，也不包含外星人的情况
for, and that broke something.
于是一些东西被破坏了
So these are some side effects of immutability that don't make us happy.
所以这些是可变性的一些副作用
那不会让我们开心
Let's try doing things the immutable way.
让我们尝试以不变的方式做事
So in an immutable world, my array, my zoo, once I've created it, it just sits and is
所以在一个不变的世界里，我的数组，我的动物园，一旦我创建了它，它就像石头一样呆在那儿
forever.
永远
I cannot change it.
我无法更改
What I can do if I want a new zoo that's more exotic is I can make a copy that's the same
如果我想要一个更有异国情调的新动物园，我可以复制副本
size as my original array, and I can make the modification I want, so I can put my alien
大小与原始数组一样，我可以做想要的修改，于是我把我的外星人
in there in place of the rabbit.
放在那里代替兔子。
And so this is pretty sweet because now my co-worker is maybe, and they're, like, whoo
所以这很不错，因为现在我的同事会说，哇
nothing broke in my program, and it's all still animal creatures but I had to copy over
我的程序没被破坏，仍然是动物，但我不得不复制
that whole array.
整个数组
I had to allocate the space for that entire array, even all of the stuff that didn't change.
我必须为整个数组申请空间，甚至所有不变的东西
I had to copy all of that over, as well.
我也必须全部复制
So this means that my code runs pretty slow.
因此，这意味着我的代码运行得很慢
And it also takes up a lot of memory.
而且它还占用大量内存
It takes up a lot of space and time.
它占用大量空间和时间
The complexity on those things are bad because copying is a waste of both time and space.
这些事情的复杂性不好，因为
复制是浪费时间和空间。
It makes us sad face!
它使我们悲伤！
We don't want that.
我们不想那样
So if we want to do immutability, we must be able to find a better way of doing that.
因此，如果要实现不变性，我们必须
能够找到一种更好的方法
Luckily for us, a lot of very smart folks have been thinking very hard about this problem
对我们来说幸运的是，很多非常聪明的人
一直在认真思考这个问题
for a while, and they've come up with some really good solutions for how we can deal
他们想出了一些非常好的解决方案
with immutability efficiently.
关于有效的实现不变性
immutable data structures!
不变的数据结构！
So immutable data structures is a term that you may have heard about, with functional
因此，不变的数据结构是一个术语，
你可能已经听说过
programming, or also in terms of React where they come in handy.
在函数式编程中，或者就React而言
他们派上用场了
Technically, an immutable data structure is like the rock, it just sits, and is once you
理论上说，不变的数据结构是就像石头一样，它就坐着
create it.
一旦你创造它
It never changes.
它永远不会改变
But also hear the term persistent data structures banged about.
但是经常也可以听到术语“持久数据结构”
Sometimes these are used interchangeably, but they have slightly different meanings.
有时这些可以互换使用，但它们的含义略有不同
So if immutable data is data that never changes, persistent data is data for which we have
因此，如果不可变数据是永远不变的数据，
持久数据是我们
access to old versions.
能访问其旧版本的数据
So as we've been creating new modified versions of our data structures, we keep the old versions
因此，由于我们一直在创建新的修改版本
的同时
around.
我们保留了旧版本
You might hear about partially persistent data structures where we can look at the old
你可能听说过部分持久性，我们可以查看旧的数据版本
versions, we can access them, but we can't go back and update any of them.
我们可以访问它们，但不能返回并更新其中任何一个
All we can update is the most current version that we have.
我们只能更新最新版本
And then you might also hear about fully persistent data structures where we can actually time
然后你可能还听说过完全持久数据结构
travel, we can go back and update any of our past versions.
我们可以时间旅行，回去更新我们的任何
过去的版本
And if this is starting to ring a bell like it's version control like git, it's sort of
如果这让你想起了像git这样的版本控制
the same idea.
他们其实是同样的想法
So we're going to talk about these as persistent immutable data structures, they're both persistent
因此，我们将这些称为持久不可变数据结构，它们是持久的
and immutable.
并且是不变的
Let's see how this works.
让我们看看它是如何工作的
The key to all of this is we want the old versions of our data, like, my original zoo
所有这些的关键是，我们想要旧的数据版本，例如我的原始动物园
to stay put.
保持不变
We just want to to sit like the rock but we want new versions to be created efficiently.
我们只是想让它像岩石一样坐着，但是我们
希望有效地创建新版本
So what magical tricks do we have to use to, like, make this happen?
因此，我们使用什么魔法做到这一点？
Do we have to make invocations do dances to the gods of space and time complexity?
我们是否必须祈祷，对着时间和空间复杂性之神跳舞？
No.
不
It's very simple.
非常简单
Trees and sharing.
树结构和共享
Isn't that sweet?
这不香吗？
These two simple concepts will get us efficient immutable data.
这两个简单的概念带给我们高效的不变数据
How?
怎么做的？
So let's talk about trees because trees rock pretty hard, as well, alternative, unfortunately
所以我们来谈谈树，因为树木也很酷
I don't have a poem for that, sorry.
但是很遗憾我没有诗
Imagine that we could find a way to represent our zoo array as a tree.
想象一下，我们可以把我们的动物园表示为一棵树
So one thing I could do is I could put all of my animals -- all of my values -- in the
所以我可以做的一件事就是我可以把所有
我所有的动物-我所有的值
leaves of a tree, and I could make it so that each leaf holds one value, one animal.
放在一棵树的叶子，我可以做到每片叶子拥有一个值，一只动物。
But they might get lonely, so let's put them with a buddy.
但是他们可能会变得寂寞，所以让我们把它们和一个伙伴放在一起。
Let's put them 2x2.
让我们把它们每两个放在一起
So each of our leaves will have two values and we'll hope that the buddies get along
所以我们的每一片叶子都有两个值。我们希望朋友们相处融洽
and not each each other -- looking at you, tiger, number six, don't eat that koala, and
而不是彼此-我说你呢老虎，6号，不要吃考拉
we can go up to intermediate nodes up and up, until we get to the root node of the whole
我们可以上升到中间节点，直到我们到达整体的根节点
structure, and now that root is an array represented previously by a tree.
现在根是一个表示为一棵树的数组
So this is my tree now in this structure.
所以这是我现在的树
So given this type of structure, how do we update something?
鉴于这种类型的结构，我们如何更新数据？
Given that my data is immutable, and it can never change, how can I handle the fact that
鉴于我的数据是不可变的，并且它永不改变，我该如何处理
it has an alien in it.
它里面有一个外星人
So here what I would do is I would take the node that contains the value that I want to
所以在这里我要做的是，找出
change.
我要更改的节点
So in this case it would be the 0/1 node that you see on the bottom of the screen.
因此，在这种情况下，将是0/1节点，会在屏幕底部看到
And so I make a new copy where I've still got my monkey but I've changed the rabbit
所以我创造了一个副本。里面有我的猴子，但我把
to an alien.
兔子换成了外星人
And then I need to copy any of the intermediate nodes in the tree that were pointing to the
然后我需要复制所有指向节点的中间节点
node that I changed.
我想要更改的节点
So I basically trace a path up towards the root of the tree, which, now, I've got a new
所以我基本上找到一条通往根的路径，现在，
root, which means another version of the data structure.
我有了新的根，表示数据的另一个版本
So this technique of making this update by copying the path from the leaf I changed to
因此，这种复制从我更改为的叶子到根结点的做法
the root is called path copying.
称为路径复制
That's pretty cool because now I didn't have to copy the entire array; I just had to copy
那很酷，因为现在我没有复制整个数组，我只需要复制
the nodes on the way from the root to the leaf that I changed.
从根到我改变的叶子之间的节点
So if we've turned in something linear and copying into something logarithm.
因此，时间复杂度从O(N)变成O(logN)
That's pretty cool, that's more performant, and the data of this is that all of these
这很酷，性能更高。数据是所有这些
nodes in yellow here, so most of the tree is shared between the two versions, between
节点是黄色的，所以大部分树在两个版本之间共享
the old version and the new.
旧版本和新版本
And so this saves me a lot of space because I can actually reuse the parts of the original
因此，这为我节省了很多空间，因为
我实际上可以重用原始的部分
version that didn't change, whereas, before, I had to copy those over, as well.
版本没有变化，而以前我也必须复制这些内容
So this means that what was before, like, a lot of memory consumption becomes a lot
所以这意味着内存的消耗变小了
smaller because you don't have to store as many copies of the things if they didn't change.
因为你不必复制没有改变的东西
And that's called structural changing because we're sharing the structure of the tree between
这就是所谓的结构变更，因为我们共享树的结构
the two versions.
在两个版本之间
So we've been talking about updating things but how do we get at the values in our data
所以我们一直在谈论更新事物，但是我们如何获得数据中的值
structure?
How do we access them?
我们如何访问它们？
Well, it turns out this isn't just a tree, it's a special type of tree called a TRIE
好吧，事实证明这不仅仅是树，这是一种叫做TRIE的特殊树结构
tree, which originally came from the world "retrieval," so people could, I guess, call
最初来自单词“检索”，所以我猜人们可以
it tree, which is funny because we also call TREE trees, so we can call them "tries" if
称呼它是树，为了避免混淆，我叫它TRIE（音同try）
we want.
So a try is a type of tree, where the leaves represent the values, and the paths to the
TRIE是一种树，叶子代表值，到达叶子节点的路径
value are the keys that that data is associated with.
是值相关的键值
So often you see TRIEs with values stored as keys.
因此，TRIE经常用单词当作键
So, for example, if I have T stored as a key, what I do to get to the T is I trace the tree
因此，例如，如果我将tea作为键，如果要找到它，我要做的就是遍历树
one letter at a time.
一次一个字母
Then I go to T, and then to E, and then to EA, is my key, and then my value there is
然后我去T，然后去E，然后去
EA，是我的键，然后我的值就是
three.
Because everything at the end sounds like "ee" in this talk.
因为在本次演讲中所有的句子都以“ ee”结尾。
So this is pretty cool, but in our data structure, we weren't using words, we just wanted an
所以这很酷，但是在我们的数据结构中，
我们不会用单词作为键，我们只是想要一个
array-type thing, we wanted indeces, right?
数组类型的东西，我们想要索引，对吗？
So the insight here is if we treat the index as a binary number, then we can pretend that
所以这里的想法是如果我们把索引作为一个二进制数，那么我们可以假装
that's kind of, like, our word and we can descend the tree, bit-by-bit as if each representation
就像我们的单词，我们可以一位一位的逐渐查找树
of our binary representation is a letter.
我们的二进制表示形式是一个字母
So let's see how that works.
因此，让我们看看它是如何工作的。
If I'm trying to get at item five in my array, so the animal at index five, I'd convert that
如果我想获得数组中的第5项，因此，索引为5的动物将转换为
to binary, so that's one, zero, one, and then I step through that as if it was a word.
二进制，所以是1，0，1，然后我一步一步地仿佛是一个单词。
I step through it letter-by-letter, bit-by-bit.
我一步一步地经过每个数位
So I go from the root to the branch.
所以我从根到分支
I have a choice of either zero or one.
我可以选择0或者1
I go to branch one first.
我先去一个分支
And then I go to branch zero, and then I take the thing on the one side.
然后我去0分支，然后我去1。
So I go one, zero, one, down my tree and then I end up at my frog at index five.
所以我沿着树走1，0，1。我最终在索引5处找到了青蛙
So this is a pretty simple insight but it ends up being incredibly powerful because
所以这是一个非常简单的想法，但是最终变得非常强大，因为
it allows us to quickly traverse this tree structure, which lets us use that structural
它使我们能够快速遍历这棵树，让我们能够
sharing to more efficiently represent our new copies of our immutable data structure.
更有效的共享。使之代表我们最新的数据
And, importantly, we don't have to be using a binary tree, meaning we have two branches
而且，重要的是，我们不必使用一棵二叉树，意味着我们每个节点有两个分支
from each node.
That fits pretty well on a slide, but actually what you mostly see is a 32-way branching.
二叉树非常适合幻灯片，但实际上你最常看到的是32向分支
So in our trees that we've been looking at, we've kind of had one bit of information per
所以看上去我们在树的每一级只有一点信息
level.
水平。
And we've been descending bit-by-bit but if we had a 32-way branching tree, it would be
而且我们一直在逐位下降，但是如果我们有一棵32向分支树
five bits of information that we would be representing at each level.
在每一级我们将获得的5点信息
So that would look something like this.
这样看起来像这样
If we had a much bigger number, like, 18,977, in binary, that's that bunch of ones and zeros.
如果我们有更大的数字，例如18,977，在二进制中，就是一堆0和1
This would be a really deep tree if I had to descend into it one at a time, it would
如果用二叉树表示，这将是一棵非常深的树
be like 15 levels deep.
有15层
Too much, too long.
太多，太久
So if I'd make more branches at each level, then I can chunk this up into kind of 5-bit
因此，如果我要在每个级别建立更多分支，
我可以将其分成5位
letters as it were, and descend the tree that it's now only three levels using the 32-way
字母，用32路的话实际只有3层分支
branching.
So this is kind of a tradeoff between how deep your tree is going to be, and how big
这是树的深度和广度之间的取舍
the nodes are going to be because if I have just one bit of information at each level
节因为如果我有每个级别只有一位信息
then I have really small nodes.
那我的节点很小
That's quick to copy over but I have to go very, very deep down in the tree for a larger
复制很快，但如果数组很大的话我的路径会很深
array.
And generally, research has found that 32 is a pretty good tradeoff between the depth
研究发现32在深度和广度之间是一个很好的权衡
of the tree.
So what we've seen is a bitmap vector TRIE.
因此，我们看到的是位图矢量TRIE
That's just jargon.
那只是行话
We don't need to care about that.
我们不需要关心
But if you need something to Google, you can Google that.
但是，如果你想Google，可以用这个关键字
This is cool for array-type of things and we have an index we want to jump there, but
对于数组类型的东西这很酷，因为一旦有了索引我们能跳到那儿
what about objects?
那对象呢？
We also want to be able to associate objects with arbitrary keys, not just indeces, so
我们还希望能够关联对象使用任意键，而不仅是索引
we want non-integers as keys, how does that work?
我们希望非整数作为键，那怎么做？
So if I want a version of my data structure where it's no longer an array but it's something
所以如果我想要一个数据结构的版本，它不再是数组
like an object where I'm associated letters with each of my animals like M for monkey
而是对象。就像我的每只动物，例如M代表猴子，
and P for panda, et cetera, what I can do is I can take my keys, in this case, they're
P代表熊猫，等等。我可以拿我的键-是字符串
letters, and hash them to get a number that represents the key.
对它们进行哈希处理以获得一个数字代表字母
So that each key will have its own number.
这样每个键都有自己的编号
They won't be in order necessarily, but that's okay.
他们不一定有序，但这没关系
Objects don't have to be in order.
对象属性不需要有序
And then we can use the hash of that number in binary to descend the tree as before.
我们可以使用该数字的哈希值用二进制表示，然后去搜索树
So if I wanted to look up the value associated with key "F," I could hash F, get some number
因此，如果我想查找键“ F”关联的值，我可以对F进行哈希处理，得到一些数字
and let's say I get five, like, A, B, C, D, E, five.
假设我有五个，例如A，B，C，D，E，五个
And that would be represented in binary as one, and I descend the tree as before, here
那将用二进制表示为1，我像以前一样向下搜索
for simplicity, just using a one bit at a time, two-way branching tree.
为了简单起见，我们使用双向分支树，每次只有一位
But typically we would be doing this with 32 branches per level.
但是通常我们会这样做每级32个分支
So, again, we just descend the tree using the binary representation of our key, in this
因此，我们根据键的二进制表示搜索树
case, we used a hash function to transform it from some arbitrary object into a number
这样一来，我们使用了哈希函数来把任意对象转换成一个数字
and we get the animal we want -- in this case, our frog.
我们得到了我们想要的动物-这里具体指我们的青蛙。
Cool.
酷
So that, if you want to Google it, the thing you could Google is a hash array mapped TRIE.
这样，如果你想搜索，可以Google“哈希数组映射TRIE”
And this was a data structure parented by Phil Bagwell, and Rich Hickey, kind of started
这个数据结构由菲尔·巴格韦（Phil Bagwell）和里奇·希基（Rich Hickey）发明
using it, and a lot of these an implemented in languages like Clojure to implement the
并使用，其中很大部分在Clojure之类的语言中已经实现了
data efficiently.
用来提高效率
There's a ton of optimizations that are usually done on these data structures to make them
通常在这些数据结构上会做很多优化
super-duper fast and lots of details that we're not covering here but this is the basic
使它们速度超快，还有很多细节我们不在这里介绍，但这是基本的理念
idea.
Trees to represent our data, structural sharing so that we can reuse as much information as
用树来表示数据，结构共享。这样我们就可以重复使用尽可能多的信息
possible between the old versions and the new versions.
在旧版本和新版本之间
And this idea of using binary representations of our keys, whether indeces, or hashed keys
还有使用二进制表示我们的键，无论是索引还是被哈希处理的单词
to descend the tree to find the thing we're looking for.
去树中查找
So to recap, mutability induces headaches.
综上所述，可变性让人头疼
It is to be avoided especially if you're doing functional programming where the essential
做函数式编程时尤其要避免
idea is to not have side effects and only be using pure functions that don't change
因为函数式变成就是关于避免副作用，只使用纯函数
anything except do the computation on the input and return the output.
纯函数除了计算输入输出之外不改变任何东西
Immutability, on the other hand, is great because if I'm using immutable data, I can't
另一方面，不变性很好，因为如果我使用不可变数据
mess up my co-worker's program by making the zoo she only thought was animals suddenly
我就不会搞乱同事的程序，她以为只有动物的动物园里
have an alien in it.
里面有一个外星人
But copying is a really bad way of handling data because it is not efficient neither with
但是复制是一种非常糟糕的处理方式
数据，因为它不高效
respect to time, nor space.
时间复杂度和空间复杂度上都是
And structural sharing, using these tree structures
-- or TRIE structures, and sharing as much
结构共享，使用这些树结构-或TRIE结构，并尽可能多地共享
information from one version to the next is the really performant way to do this.
从一个版本到下一个版本的信息是真正有效的方法
And so you're probably thinking, okay, these data structures are pretty cool.
所以你可能在想，好吧，这些数据结构非常酷
But what am I supposed to do with them?
但是我该怎么用呢？
I'm not going to be building boxes of emoji here, am I?
我不会建造表情符号的盒子，不是吗
No, you don't have to.
不，你不必。
In JavaScript, there are some really great libraries out there to help you use these
在JavaScript中，有一些很棒的库可以帮助你使用这些数据结构
right off the bat.
马上就可以
There are various solutions but I'm going to talk about a couple of them.
有各种解决方案，但我要谈论其中的几个
So one is called Mori.
所以一个叫做Mori
Mori is basically a port of Clojure script by David Nolan that allows you to leverage
Mori基本上是ClojureScript的移植，作者是大卫·诺兰（David Nolan）
the implementations of these data structures from ClojureScript, which is the version of
这些数据结构的实现来自ClojureScript
Clojure which targets JavaScript from the comfort of your vanilla JavaScript.
ClojureScript把Clojure编译成原生JavaScript
And it's got a bit more of a Clojure feel to it.
而且还有Clojure的感觉
A bit more of a functional language feel.
有点函数式语言的感觉
The API is functional and we're going to see what that looks like in a moment.
它的API是函数式的，我们即将看到
But that's one thing that kind of sets this library apart.
但这把它和其他的库区分开
On the other hand, there's also Immutable.js.
另一方面，还有Immutable.js。
This is a library put out by Facebook.
这是Facebook推出的
It was created by Lee Byron.
它是由李·拜伦（Lee Byron）创建的
And this is a JavaScript implementation of these data structures.
这是一个JavaScript实现的数据结构
So it has a bit more of that native JavaScript feel to it.
因此，它具有更多的原生JavaScript的感觉
It doesn't have kind of the Clojure background brought in.
它没有Clojure背景
And that means it's got a more object-oriented style API, although it is still returning
这意味着它具有更多的面向对象样式的API，尽管它仍在返回
new versions of data structures instead of changing mutable structures in place.
新版本的数据结构，而不是原位改变数据
So let's see what those look like.
因此，让我们看看它们的用法
This is how you might use Mori to create what's called a vector.
这就是使用Mori来创建向量
A vector is the data structure from Mori that you'd probably be using as an array-type thing.
向量是Mori的数据结构，你可能当成数组类型去用。
So I've got a vector that I'm calling A because it's sort of array-ish.
所以我有一个向量，我称之为a，因为这有点像数组。
It's got one and two in it.
它里面有1和2。
And if I want to push something onto that, the function that I'd use is conj.
如果我想在里面添加，我要使用的函数是conj
This is from the Clojure called, Lisp-speak.
这是来自Clojure世界的Lisp语言
And what I would put in is the original A, and then what I want, which is, in this case
我要添加到A中，然后我想要的是添加3
three.
And you'll see that this creates this new structure on the right.
你会看到右边，这创建了新的数据
These vector, one, two, and one, two, three, they look different because they're not really
这些向量[1 2]和[1 2 3]，它们看起来和JavaScript的数组不太一样，因为它们不是真的
JavaScript arrays although you can convert back and forth.
JavaScript数组，它们是向量，虽然可以互相转换
But the point is this cong function returns a new value which I can catch as A2 and I
但是重点是这个conj函数返回新的值a2
can prove to myself that my original A didn't change by using the count function to see
我能证明我原来的a没有改变，通过使用count函数
how many things are in it.
看里面有几个成员
And there's only two things in it.
而且其中只有两个
But I can prove that my version, A2, has the third thing by trying to access, by using
但是我可以证明我的版本a2有第三个成员，通过使用
the get function to trying to get two, which it tells me, it is indeed three.
get函数来获取get(a2, 2)，它告诉我，确实是3
This is the same thing that you would use in Immutable.js.
在Immutable.js中也一样
Here you would use Immutable.js.list.of, that's interesting syntax.
这里使用Immutable.js的list.of，有趣的语法
But it creates something more like a JavaScript array.
但是它创建了更像JavaScript的数组
Although it is not an array, it is a JS list.
尽管它不是数组，但它是一个JS列表
That I'll call an array and if I want to add something onto a new version of A, I use this
我把那叫做a，如果我想添加一些东西在a的新版本中
sort of dot-method notation that we're used to.
我们使用点方法，这种方法我们很熟悉
I'd say a.push(3), but, importantly, this is not changing a.
我会说a.push(3)，但重要的是，a没有改变
It's just returning a new value of a, which I'm going to capture as a2 and I can prove
它只是返回a的新值，我赋值给a2，我可以证明
to myself that it didn't change.
它没有改变
A.size tells me it's two, and if I try to get the item at index two, I find that it's
a.size告诉我是两个，如果我尝试
得到索引2的成员，我发现它是3
three, as I expected.
正如我所料。
So, similarly, for what are called maps, which is kind of the key-value object that we might
因此，类似地，说到map，是我们可能会想到的键值对象
be using, if I create an object, o, which is going to be my Mori hashmap data structure
如果我创建一个对象，o，Mori的哈希表数据结构，
I'm associating a is one, b with two, again, we see that the syntax is a little different
我将a赋值1，将b赋值2，我们看到语法有点不同
from our regular JavaScript beastlier not regular JavaScript objects.
不是我们的常规JavaScript语法，因为它不是JavaScript对象。
They're super special immutable data structures, they need special syntax.
它们是超特殊的不可变数据结构，他们需要特殊的语法
And so if I want to change the value of one of my keys, I can use this asoc function
因此，如果我想更改一个键的值，我可以使用这个assoc函数
and then change the value of three in my new version, o2, and then I can prove to myself
然后在o2中改变a的值为3，然后我可以证明
that the original didn't change by using the get function to make sure that a in the original
原来的值没有改变，通过get函数得到键a的值
one -- o, is one, and the a in o2 is three, as I would expect.
在o中a是1，而o2中的a是3，正如我所期望的
And it looks quite similar in Immutable.js except the structure is called map, not hashmap
在Immutable.js中看起来非常相似，除了结构称为map而不是hashmap之外
and I can pass in a little JavaScript object, and it gives me a little o, a little more
我可以传入一个JavaScript对象，它返回o，它看上去
JavaScript syntax than we're used to.
更像我们熟悉的JavaScript的语法
This has a bit more of a syntax and feel that you might be used to from JavaScript programming
我们可能已经习惯了JavaScript编程
I can use the set method on o to create a new version where a is now three, and I can
我可以在o上使用set方法来创建一个新版本，其中a现在是3
use the get methods on my old version o, and my new-version o2 to prove to myself that
我可以在我的旧版本o上使用get方法，我得到的o2可以证明
the old one didn't change.
旧的值没有改变
So these are really immutable data structures.
因此，这些实际上是不可变的数据结构
They look really weird if you try to look at them in the console just as JavaScript
如果你试着在控制台中，把这些数据结构作为JavaScript对象那样去查看，看起来很奇怪
objects.
They're really fun to kind of poke down into because they have this complicated tree structure.
查看它们的这种复杂的树结构很有意思
So I highly recommend that you try out these libraries and see what works for you.
因此，我强烈建议你尝试这些库，看看有什么适合你
I can tell you really just briefly before I run out of time here, that how they compare
我可以很简单地告诉你，因为我快没时间了，他们的区别
is basically, again, Mori is from the Clojure world, it's ClojureScript.
基本上，Mori也是来自Clojure世界，这是ClojureScript
But the Immutable.js has more of the o.get() kind of feel to it, if you're comfortable
但是Immutable.js具有更多的类似o.get()的API
writing JavaScript like that.
如果你已经习惯JavaScript语法，会觉得很顺手
However, for me, it gives me a little bit of a cognitive dissonance there because it
但是，对我来说，我有一点认知失调是因为
looks like we're mutating things with those calls -- we're not -- but for me, to get more
看起来我们正在改变数据。我们不是-但是对我来说
into the mindset of functional programming, I prefer the functional programming of Mori
为了获得更多函数式编程的思维方式，我更喜欢Mori的函数式编程
because it gets to the way that we conceive things as inputs and not just outs.
因为它提供了一种想法数据不只是输出，也是输入
We don't want to be in the mindset of making changes in place to objects.
我们不想成为原地修改对象
There's also some minor performance differences between the two, Mori is a bit faster, and
两者之间也有一些小的性能差异，Mori的速度更快
Immutable.js is a bit smaller.
但是Immutable.js体积较小
But they're both great options, try them out, and I hope one of them works for you.
但是它们都是不错的选择，尝试一下，我希望你能用上
So that's my talk.
这就是我的演讲
I hope it's been useful.
我希望它会有用
Go forth and don't mutate your data!
继续，不要改变你的数据
这里有一些参考资料，谢谢
Here's some references for you.